RG 074:033, Theodore A. Bingham Genealogical Papers
Connecticut State Library
Theodore A. Bingham genealogical papers
1899-1932
Connecticut State Library
Bingham, Theo. A. (Theodore Alfred), 1858-1934
2 cubic feet
Includes the manuscript of The Bingham family in the United States and other material related to the Bingham Family of Andover, Conn.
RG074_033
T003243
Biographical Note
Theodore A. Bingham was born at Andover, Conn. on May 14, 1858 to Joel Foote Bingham, a clergyman, and Susan G. Bingham. He married Lucile Rutherford of St. Louis, who died in 1920. In 1926 he was married in London to Addison Mitchell of New York. She died a year later. Bingham died at his summer home in Chester, Nova Scotia, on September 7, 1934, aged 76. He was buried in Chester according to his wishes.
Bingham graduated from West Point Military Academy in 1879, receiving a commission as second lieutenant. Between 1879 and 1890 he served in various capacities as an engineering officer and as a military attaché in Berlin and Rome. He served as superintendent of the public buildings and grounds at Washington from 1897 to 901 with the rank of colonel. He was transferred to Buffalo on an engineering assignment where he suffered an accident which caused the loss of a leg, forcing his retirement from active service in the Army in 1904 at the rank of brigadier general. He served as police commissioner of New York City from January 1, 1905 to July 1, 1909. In 1911 he served for a few months as chief engineer of the Department of Highways and from 1911 to 1915 was a consulting engineer with the Department of Bridges. In 1917 he was recalled to active service in the Army, in command of the Second Engineering District, New York City. He was discharged from active service and returned to retirement on June 10, 1919
Source: "Gen. Bingham Conn. Native, Dies Aged 76" Hartford Courant, 1934 September 7, 4.
Scope and Content
Includes the manuscript version of The Bingham Family in the United States: Especially of the State of Connecticut; Including Notes on the Binghams of Philadelphia and of Irish Descent, Medieval Records, Armorial Bearings, Etc., with the prospectus and correspondence concerning its publication, as well as correspondence of genealogy data sent to Theodore A. Bingham. Also included is material on the Bingham homestead in Andover, Conn. and manuscript notes on the Bingham family in Andover and Lebanon, Conn.
Related Material
Bingham family: History and Genealogy Unit Special Genealogical File, 1712-1927
Index Terms
Persons:
Bingham, Theo. A. (Theodore Alfred), 1858-1934
Family Names:
Bingham family
Places:
Connecticut -- Genealogy
Subjects:
Bingham, Thomas, 1642-1730 -- Family
Document Types:
Correspondence; Genealogies; News clippings
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Bingham genealogy, 1899-1932
  - The Bingham family in the United States: especially of the state of Connecticut; including notes on the Binghams of Philadelphia and of Irish descent, medieval records, armorial bearings, etc., 1925 January 1; manuscript
    The published version is available at.
    - Volume 1 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Volume 2 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Volume 3 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Volume 4 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - Volume 5 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Volume 6 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - Volume 7 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    - Volume 8 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Volume 9 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - Volume 10 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    - Index (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Publication material (Box 1)
    - Prospectus, 1899, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1928-1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Mailing list, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bingham genealogy pamphlets, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1924-1928 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - English medieval Binghams, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Bingham homestead, 1905-1910, undated
  - Andover Conn., Bingham homestead, the house, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Andover Conn., Bingham farm, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Report on Phelp-Bingham farm, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Property maps, 1905, 1910, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Architectural plans and photograph, 1908, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Bingham families in Andover and Lebanon, 1911, undated
  - Brief history of Andover entitled, "Andover, Tolland Co., Conn.", undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Genealogical records of Andover Binghams entitled, "Andover, Tolland Co., Conn.", undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Property records of Binghams in Andover and Lebanon, undated (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Old cemetery at Andover Center, Tolland Co., Conn., undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Inscriptions in Townsend Cemetery, Andover, Tolland Co., Conn., 1911 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Genealogical record of Theodore Bingham, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Family history of Stephen Bingham, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Newspaper clippings, 1905-1932
- Miscellaneous, 1899-1920
  - 1659 Norwich Town, Conn. Some proprietors' original home lots / compiled by Theodore A. Bingham with Charles E. Chandler and Edna E. Rogers, 1920; typescript, 2 copies, 1 missing a map (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Coat of arms, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gravestones of Thomas and Mary Bingham, undated; glass negatives (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Hebron map and pictures, 1908, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Coventry, Hebron and Lebanon: Corner where these towns come together located in Andover, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Genealogy charts of Elizabeth and Dorothy Pugsley, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Descendents of Ralph Bugg of Nott, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Printed material, 1909-1920, undated
  - Map of Yorkshire / John Bartholomew, undated (Box 3)
  - Memoirs of the Binghams / Rose E. McCalmont, 1915 (Box 3)
    Inscription on verso of front endsheet: "Gen. Theo. A. Bingham / U S Army / N.Y. - Feb. 11/18 / see p. 169 which is the Conn. family".
  - The Old Lee house / Celeste E. Bush, 1917 (Box 3)
  - Pocket map of Sheffield / printed by Pawson & Brailsford, undated (Box 3)
  - Records and record searching: a guide to the genealogist and topographer / Walter Rye, 1888 (Box 3)
  - Story of Bride Brook (Box 3)
    Inscription on recto of front cover: "Compliments of Bride Brook Farm folks Mr. & Mrs. Harry Bennitt Hunt 1924".
  - The story of the English towns: Nottingham / E. L. Guilford, 1920 (Box 3)
  - The story of the English towns: Sheffield / J.S. Fletcher, 1919 (Box 3)
  - Visitation of England and Wales, volume 16/ edited by Frederick Arthur Crisp, 1909 (Box 3)
    Inscriptions on verso of front endsheet: "Gen. Theo. A. Bingham / WSA" and "T.A.B. / Nov. 19 '31 / London / p.30".